Finding Aid for James F. Coakley Papers, 1966-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James F. Coakley papers 1966-1971
Coakley, James F.
1 linear foot
2009185 Aa 2
James F. Coakley was an assistant professor in the Department of Speech at the University of Michigan from 1966 to1971. Focusing mainly in theatre and literary interpretation, he was responsible for directing and managing many of the plays that were put on by the University Players during his time at the University of Michigan. Notable productions include The Homecoming, Lysistrata, Much Ado About Nothing, and Arthur Miller's After the Fall. Includes photographs from a 1967 production of After the Fall where Arthur Miller was present. Also scrapbooks, photos, and slides from other productions by the University of Michigan's University Players during 1966-1971.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was received in October 2009 (donor 10281 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
James Francis Coakley was born on December 12, 1933, in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. He earned his BFA at the Carnegie Mellon Institute of Technology in 1955. From 1956 to 1958, he served in the U.S. Army Signal Corps working as a cryptographer. In 1959, he earned his MA from the University of Minnesota, and soon after earned his Ph.D. from Northwestern University in 1964. During his years as a student, he earned a Mellon Scholarship while attending the Carnegie Mellon Institute of Technology, a graduate scholarship from Northwestern University, and a Woodrow Wilson Dissertation Year Fellowship.
In the late 1950s and early 1960s, Coakley was involved in many local theaters (in Northport, NY, Pittsburgh, PA, and at the University of Minnesota), serving either as director or stage manager.
Coakley first taught at Loyola University, then the University of Michigan, and concluded his teaching career at Northwestern University. He also taught for a short time at Roosevelt University, and served as a visiting professor at the Art Institute of Chicago.
While at the University of Michigan, Coakley taught classes on the technical aspects of theatre, and was in charge of the stage design or directorship for major productions of the Speech Department, such as The Homecoming, Lysistrata, Much Ado About Nothing, and After the Fall. Some of his research topics included Shakespeare promptbooks and Shaw-Craig literary and theatrical relations.
Coakley was a member of many theatre-related organizations, including the American Educational Theatre Association, the Speech Association of America, the American National Theatre and Academy, and the Shaw Society.
The collection provides some documentation of plays Coakley staged with the University Players, notably Arthur Millers After the Fall, and lecture notes for courses he taught. The collection is organized into three series: "After the Fall", Photographic Slides, Speech 230 “The Arts of the Theatre” and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Coakley, James F.; Drama.; Miller, Arthur, 1915-2005.; Theater--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Speech.; University of Michigan--Dramatics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University Players (University of Michigan)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Coakley, James F.; Miller, Arthur, 1915-2005.; Theatrical productions.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Speech.; University Players (University of Michigan)
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.; Photographs.
- "After the Fall," 1967
  The "After the Fall" series is composed of a binder of black and white photographs from the performance of Arthur Miller's play in March 1967. Arthur Miller was present during this particular performance, and is visible in many of the photographs. The first folder contains the cover of the original binder that housed the photographs. It was saved because there is a label on the cover that describes the contents of the binder. The remaining folders contain the photographs themselves, removed from their original cardboard backings.
  - "After the Fall" binder cover, 1967 (Box 1)
  - "After the Fall" scrapbook photographs, 1967, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Slides
  The Slides series contains three folders of Kodachrome slides from the plays Coakley was involved with, ranging from the years 1966 to 1971. The names of the plays are usually written on the slides themselves. The plays include Camino Real, Sgt. Musgrave's Dance, The Homecoming, The Ghost Sonata ,Major Barbara ,Lysistrata, Of Mice and Men, Much Ado About Nothing, The Balcony ,Plough, and an unidentified play from 1970 to 1971.
  - "Camino Real," "Serjeants Musgrave's Dance," "The Homecoming," "The Ghost Sonata," "Major Barbara," "Lysistrata, 1970" (Box 1)
  - "Of Mice and Men," "Much Ado About Nothing," "The Balcony," "The Plough and the Stars," 1970 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
- Speech 230 "The Arts of the Theatre"
  The Speech 230 series contains four folders of lecture notes from a class called "The Arts of the Theatre" taught by Coakley. The course surveyed the arts and crafts which contribute to theatrical performance. The notes cover many aspects of conducting a stage production (directing, acting, stage design, analysis of plays, etc).
  - Lecture Notes, ca. 1969, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbooks series contains four scrapbooks with reviews, articles, photographs, and programs from plays that Coakley was involved with, dating from 1966 to 1971. The productions featured the University of Michigan University Players. The majority of the material is pasted to the scrapbook pages, although some have separated. The photographs are either silver halide, color, or Polaroid.
  - University Players, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - University Players, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - University Players, 1968 (Box 1)
  - University Players, 1969-1971 (Box 1)